<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great grievance of Scotland, the mother and nurse of many evils to church and state. Together with a rational proposal, a suitable expedient, and the proper remedy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218497</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830083</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830083</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34532</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41901)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34532)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1778:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great grievance of Scotland, the mother and nurse of many evils to church and state. Together with a rational proposal, a suitable expedient, and the proper remedy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23 [i.e. 25], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edenburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year MDCLXXXIX. [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 25 misnumbered 23.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34532:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT GRIEVANCE OF SCOTLAND, THE Mother and Nurſe of many Evils TO CHURCH and STATE. TOGETHER With a Rational Propoſal, a Suitable Expedient, and the Proper Remedy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDENBURGH:</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34532:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34532:2"/>
            <head>THE GREAT GRIEVANCE OF SCOTLAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. THE Prelate being, 1. A Monſter in the State; 2. A Miſchief in the Church; and 3. The great Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Happineſs of both.</p>
            <p n="2">II The Prelate being both the Joy and Mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Stock, 1. of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> 2. of Atheiſts and Prophane Ruffians, and 3. of Lazy Carnal Idol-Shepherds.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Prelate being the Idol of Jealouſie, 1. between King and Nobles, 2. between King and Goſpel Miniſters, 3. between King and People, and that which provoketh God to Wrath againſt Church and State.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The Prelate being a Burthen. 1. to the Crown, on whoſe Revenues he feedeth, 2. to the Kingdom, which firſt and laſt for his ſake hath been put to ſo much needleſs Expences, 3. to Church, Schools, and Colledges, whom he hath Robbed of their Allowance and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34532:3"/>
            <p n="5">V. The Prelate being the occaſion of ſo much Trouble, Danger and Miſchief, of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Storms and Shakings, 1. to the Crown, 2. to the Kingdom, 3. to the Church and Miniſtry.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The Prelate being, 1. a Reproach and Vexation to the Nobility, 2. the great Offence and Scandal of the People, and 3. a woful Plague and Scourge of Faithful Miniſters.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. The Prelate being both the Mother and Nurſe, 1. of all Looſeneſs and Prophanity, 2. of Rebellion and Sedition, and 3. of Schiſm, Oppreſſion and Perſecution.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The Prelate being, 1: a Baſtard and Tyrannical Lord, 2. a Selfiſh and Unjuſt Judge, and 3. a Woolfiſh Shepherd to devour the Flock.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. The Prelate being, 1. one whom Men mock when they Praiſe and Applaud, 2. Fret and Chafe when they Follow and Attend, and 3. Hate and Curſe in their Heart, when they muſt open their Purſes to maintain a Standing Army to hold him up in his Grandeur, and ſtrengthen his Hands in Tyrannizing over the Faithful.</p>
            <p n="10">X. The Prelate being, 1. a Time-Server, and Self-ſeeker, 2. a Cheater and Deceiver whom none can truſt, and 3. Infamous and Self-condemned, for whom his greateſt Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites without Bluſhing cannot Plead.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. The Prelate being Unhappy. 1. to his Authors and Supporters, 2. Ungrateful to his Friends and Benefactors, and 3. Oppreſſing and Rigorous to his Vaſſals and Vicars, whom though he ſuffer to Live as they liſt, yet allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:34532:3"/> to them as little to live upon as he can.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. The Prelate being an infamous <note n="*" place="bottom">The Britiſh Prelate having his Original and Pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, 1. from Pagan Prieſts, amongſt whom were their Flamines and Arch-flamines, after which Pattern and Model (O Prelates, be aſhamed of your Nativity) and proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to whoſe number, and in whoſe Sees and Cathedrals the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops at their Erection, were placed, as their own <hi>Polyd. Virgil,</hi> in his Account of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention and Inventors of things, with many others, clearly demonſtrate; and albeit in times of Perſecution, when Presbyteries and Synods could not meet, a delegation to ſome one or more was neceſſary; yet the Britiſh Prelate (whatever claim may be alledged to Antiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by ſuch as enjoy, or are gaping after a fat Benefice) can truly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce no Pattern, but from <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Pagan Idolators;</hi> and no Warrant (whatever ſome mutter concerning a <hi>Jus Divinum</hi>) but what was granted by Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, either Abuſed, 1. by their Hypocriſy and ſubtil Inſinuation, or 2. againſt their Hearts forced to yield to what Prelates deſired; or 3. after they had Entoxicate the People with a fond Perſwaſion, that the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven was put in their Hands; and that they could admit or hold out at their diſcretion; they were put in a Capacity to require whatever their Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Avarice did prompt them to.</note> Baſtard; 1. begotten without the Conſent of the Raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mother (<hi>viz.</hi> the Church) yea (which is rare) whom ſhe will not acknowledge to be her Son, 2. who being aſhamed of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, diſowneth his Father, the King, while he pretendeth to a <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> like ſome Heroick Pagans, who to Cloak their Spurious Original, pretended they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of the Gods; And 3. thus is a Robber, in catching and poſſeſſing the Fathers Goods, whom he diſclaimeth, and the Mothers Revenues, who denyeth him, and proteſteth he is not her Son.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34532:4"/>
            <p n="13">XIII. The Prelate being, 1. brought forth in an Evil time, a time of Diſtreſs, Anguiſh, and Perſecution, 2. having begotten and brought forth ſuch a Curſed Son, the Pope and great Antichriſt, who caſt and held his Father under Foot, and Ruled all at his pleaſure; And 3. ſince the Reformation in <hi>Britain,</hi> having been always employed in ſuch a wicked Work, <hi>viz.</hi> to advance Superſtition and Will-Worſhip, to obſtruct the Purity of the Goſpel, and the Power of Godlineſs, and to Oppreſs and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Chriſts Faithful Miniſters, to rob the Church of its Liberty, to obtrude Idol Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds on Chriſts Flock, and to hold out and caſt out Faithful Paſtors, who would make it their work to feed the Flock, and not themſelves.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. The Prelate being, 1. a Cruel and Implacable Enemy, 2. an Unfaithful and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Friend, and 3. a ſixth Finger in the Hand, a Superfluous Member, as Uſeleſs and Unprofitable, ſo hurtful and pernicious both to Church and State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Were it, not then, 1. for the Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Honour and Emolument, 2. for the Kingdoms Welfare and Tranquility, and 3. for the Churches Happineſs and Vnity, to have this burthen removed, this Idol of Iealouſie caſt down, and this Stumbling-block taken out of the way? And may we not apply what was ſaid in reference</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34532:4"/> 
               <hi>to the proper <hi>Babylon</hi> and her lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Ones, to thoſe Blats of the myſtical <hi>Babylon?</hi>
               </hi> O Daughter of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who art to be deſtroyed, happy ſhall be he that rewardeth thee as thou haſt ſerved us, <hi>Pſal. 137. v. 8.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could any King have lived in greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Plenty, Proſperity, and Tranquility, then King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. or any King ſo boaſt of the Affection of his Subjects as King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. might have done, had not the Prelate ſtood in the way? The ſenſe of our Miſery in the time of our late Confuſion, our Sympathy then with his Majeſty and the Royal Family, under their Sufferings; together with the ſenſe of the Ingratitude and Miſcarriages of many, the Inſolency, Rebellion, and Treachery of others in theſe Lands, would have ſo knit the Hearts of all to His Majeſty, and made His Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſo ſweet and refreſhing, that he could not have askt what they would not have cheerfully given, nor commanded them to do what willingly they would not have done: And, O how would the Man (whoſoever he had been) who durſt have ſpoken any thing to His Majeſty's Prejudice, have been Abominated! Nay, all the Conteſt then would have been, who ſhould have moſt Cheerfully expreſs'd their Affectionate Loyalty, their High Eſteem and Reverence of His moſt Excellent Majeſty, their great Joy for His Highneſs Safety, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and Reſtauration, their care and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34532:5"/> of his Happineſs and long Reign, and their ſatisfaction with his Government, and to live under his ſhadow. Let Court Paraſites ſuggeſt what they pleaſe, the Love of the People is the beſt Pillar of the Throne. Hence His Majeſty in his firſt Speech to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, immediately after his return, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1660. wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, That <hi>He valued the Love of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more then many Crowns.</hi> And after enquiry, the Satisfaction and Affection of the Subjects will be found the ſtrongeſt Bull-work, and moſt concludent Argument againſt <hi>Defenſive Arms.</hi> For let men diſpute as they will, a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple once provok'd, finding themſelves in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to right themſelves, will (I do not now enquire whether or when they ſhould) make the Sword cut the Cords of all Bonds that would bind their Hands and bear them down; nay, the more ſtrong and pinching theſe be, they will be accounted the more Intolerable, and being caſt off, will render the diſſatisfied the more implacable. Who knows what a loſs His Majeſty was at upon the account of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction of good People, and moſt Loyal Subjects, becauſe of the Hierarchical Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Prelacy it ſelf, the Mother of theſe Abuſes, and Nurſery of Popery and Prophani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which never did, nor is likely to do any good Office to the <hi>Throne;</hi> but if the Prelat were Popular, and had Moyen with the People, and thus once were in a Capacity, would (as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he hath) be Ready to improve his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour againſt the Throne, to ſtir up to Sedition and Sound a Trumpet to Rebellion, as Mr.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34532:5"/> 
               <hi>Pryn</hi> hath fully <note n="*" place="margin">Antypathy of the Engliſh-Prelacy to Regal Monarchy, and Civil <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</note> demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in a large Volume, containing an Hiſtory of the Conſpiracies, Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Treachery of the Prelates, both Popiſh and Proteſtant, and from thence concludeth, that <hi>the Engliſh Prelates in all Ages have been the greateſt Rebels, Traytors, Conſpirators and Oppoſites to their Kings, the Chiefest Incendiaries and Firebrands which have Infeſted the Realm, and the Archeſt Tyrants and Oppreſſours of the People, and Invaders of the Laws and Liberties of all other Callings and Profeſſions of Men, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally or joyntly conſidered.</hi> And what the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of moſt of them, and the Inferiour Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy hath been, and is to this preſent King, is too well known.</p>
            <p>But, ſome will ſay, If the Prelates Wings were Clipt, he needed not be much feared: Anſwer, Tho' Moderation in Evil be more tolerable then the Exceſs; yet, who can ſay it is good and Eligible? Vertue is placed between two Extreams, but doth not partake and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row more or leſs from either: and O what a Monſter would a Moderate Prelate be, and how few his Days? How would that Impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable and Furious Creature Rage, till either he burſt aſunder, or did break all the Bonds wherewith he were bound and kept under? 2. What a Ridiculous Empty Shadow and Non-ſignificant Cypher would he be, and for what would he ſerve? He would not then be a Curb and Terrour to the Nobility, nor ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent Affairs and Perſons to his Majeſty as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34532:6"/> to make Men fawn <hi>on</hi> him, nor ſo Oppreſs the Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he hath Mettle for no other Work: Hence, 3. He would turn deſpicable, for if once he loſt his Sting none would Fear, as none do Love him; yea his own Creatures and Vicars, with the firſt would be ready to Hiſs at him, and Curſe the Day they firſt ſaw his Face. 4. As this Mongrel Prelate, would neither be for Work nor Pleaſure, ſo neither for Meat nor Medicine; ſuch an Impoyſoned Morſel, and Venomous Plaiſter, would rather breed new Diſtempers then Cure former Diſeaſes, ſuch a Hotch Potch could not ſtop the Mouths of them who now Complain, nor ſatisfie the deſires of Loyal Subjects and ſober Chriſtians, who are waiting and Praying for better things, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the occaſion of Schiſm and Confuſion, which threaten ſuch ſad things both to Church and State; Ah, may we not then ſay of that poor Creature, <hi>Cui bono Regi &amp; cui uſui Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae vel Reipublicae?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O! but if the Baſtard Prelate were once caſt out, and Presbyterian Government ſettled according to the excellent Patern held forth in other Reformed Churches, and agreed upon by both Houſes of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, and Ordered to be obſerved in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> [<hi>Die Martis</hi> 19. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1648.] What Acclamations of Joy? What expreſſions of Satisfaction and returns of thanks to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and to ſuch as had been Inſtrumental in that good Work from all Ranks of People? And how quickly would all diſloyal and Seditious Perſons be Diſcovered, how eaſily their Mouth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34532:6"/> ſtopt, and their Hands bound and ſuch become a Reproach to all, but a Terrour to none but themſelves? And they who now lurk under the honeſt Mantle of Non-conformity and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, would appear in their own Colours; ſad experience may Teach how little the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Lords can do for holding out or remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Schiſms, Hereſie and Sedition, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their Power and Violence; and how from time to time they have been the Seed and occaſion of theſe woful Evils: But Presbyterian Government, in it's due Exerciſe, would (as King <hi>James</hi> told the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelates, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this very Point, and ſhowing the Cauſe why then there were no Sectaries in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> while they abounded in <hi>England</hi>) <hi>Kill the Cocatrice in the Egg, and tho' it were Hatcht, quickly find it out and Kill it, as it were with a Look,</hi> (but not of Hierarchical Fury, but of Meekneſs, and by drawing with the Cords of Love, and the Methods held forth in Mr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough's</hi> Golden <hi>Irenicum</hi>) while all means Eſſayed for preventing Sedition in the State, and Confuſion in the Church are to no purpoſe Eſſayed; And when neither the Prelatical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, nor any State Policy or Expedient can do the turn, what we now plead for would prove effectual, and a Wedge of the ſame Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber will Cleave the Knotty Tree, that would not yield to what ſeemed to be more forcible and irreſiſtable.</p>
            <p>If ſuch as ſay, <hi>No Biſhop, no King,</hi> would ſeriouſly conſider, they might acknowledge, that with as good Reaſon it might be ſaid,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34532:7"/> 
               <hi>There could be no King, if there were none to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndermine and Ruin the Throne;</hi> and, O what a Reproach is it to the Throne to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that it can be better ſupported by the Rotten Pillar of Prelacy, then by the Divine Cords of Presbytery, which is ſo well Founded on the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>But, now waving all Extrinſical Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and abſtracting from Effects and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, yea, and from all Moral and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reſpects, let me Tender a Propoſal that may cut off all the pretended Politicians poor Pleas; and it is this [If his Majeſties Royal Prerogatives, the Liberties and Priviledges of Civil Courts, and the Honour of Nobles, be not better ſecured from Eccleſiaſtical Encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by Presbytery then Prelacy, let King and Nobles Reject this Motion;] The <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Prelates in their ſeaſonable Caſe, and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their Diſcourſes, pretended they were but the Kings Commiſſioners (and thus muſt ſtand only in a Civil Capacity) as formerly they ſaid, they were but the Church Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners for Sitting in Parliament to ſee that nothing there was concluded to the prejudice of the Church; away with ſuch unfaithful Truſtees, who neither regard a Commiſſion from Church or State, as not minding the good of either, but would Cloak a Baſtard Office with whatſoever pretence might beſt ſerve their turn; but if his Majeſty as our Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly uſed to ſend a Commiſſioner to genera Aſſembles, would be pleaſed to intruſt and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point ſome Noblemen or Worthy Gentlemen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34532:7"/> to be preſent at all Provincial, and (if it were thought needful) Claſſical Meetings, to ſee that Miniſters kept themſelves within their own Sphere, and did not medle with Civil and State Affairs; and for Maintaining a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding between Church and State, the ſweet effects and Fruits thereof might from Day to Day appear; this courſe as it would prove to all intents and purpoſes more effectual for the Magiſtrates Security then Prelacy; ſo it would be, 1. An eaſie, 2. A Cheap, 3. A Safe, and 4. A Lawful, and 5. Laudable Expedient: For, 1. No difficulty appeareth in the thing. 2. One Prelates Rent might Defray the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of all theſe Commiſſioners, for who would refuſe that Employment tho' they had but a ſmall or no Allowance, which would be rather an <hi>Honour</hi> then <hi>Onus?</hi> And why ſhould any Complain more then Elders formerly, who had no Sallary, notwithſtanding their Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at Synods and Presbyteries, and as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners would not refuſe to Attend theſe Meetings; ſo faithful Miniſters would heartily Welcome them, being glad to have ſuch Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of their Integrity. 3. Herein appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no hazard. And, 4. What can be Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected againſt ſuch an overture, which is not only ſo Plauſible, Seaſonable and Ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; But alſo, 5. Complyeth with the conſtant Practice of the Church, ſince the Magiſtrate became Chriſtian (except where Pope or Domineering Prelates have Exploded the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates Inſpection) and Care of Eccleſiaſtical Matters and Perſons; and is no other then what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34532:8"/> was offered by the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> to prevent the Calumnies of their Adverſaries, and was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renewed by the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants; who in a Treatiſe with their King, deſired, <note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Clerk</hi> from Mr. <hi>Mamard's</hi> Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Apples, <hi>pag.</hi> 90.</note> 
               <hi>that ſome one or other might be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by him to be preſent at their Aſſemblies, for prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of State Jealouſies and Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Calumnies,</hi> for which my Author Citeth <hi>John</hi> the 3.21. and much commendeth the Prudence and Candour of theſe Holy Men for making ſuch a Propoſal, which to this Day hath place there, and <note n="*" place="margin">De Polit. Eccleſ. cap. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Banoſius</hi> commends it, as being no leſs expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and profitable, for the Church, then deſirable by the Magiſtrate, and needful for Eſtabliſhing a good Order, Maintaining a good underſtanding, and for preventing dangerous Jealouſies and miſtakes on either Hand</p>
            <p>If any Object the Eccentrical Motions of Church-men during the late Inteſtine War, that doth not Quadrate with the preſent Caſe, and doth not plead againſt, but for this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which then could have no place; but ſince not a few Object the over-reachings and miſcarriages of that time againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on which we find a Divine Impreſs; ſuch would conſider that one Swallow makes not the Summer, and for that one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in Presbyters, Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi> will furniſh you with Hundreds in the Prelates; to ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the great Prelate the Pope, his Tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under Foot his Father the Emperour, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34532:8"/> making him not only hold his Stirrup, but bow the Back, and become a Foot-Stool for his Holineſs, while he Mounted up on his Horſe. 2. Who knows not that the Prelates then were the bane of Contention; and whoever were In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, they were the Cauſe and Occaſion of theſe Tumults; and being in the Chair did not, could not prevent, but their Place and Power brought on thoſe Evils. 3. Were not Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Civil Courts as deeply Involved in theſe as any Church Judicatory; yet, how Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous were it from thence to Infer there ſhould be no Parliament, nor Civil Judicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? <hi>It is</hi> (ſaid his late Majeſty <hi>Charles</hi> I.) <hi>a groſs Vulgar Errour to impute to or revenge upon the Function the faults of times or perſons; which Seditions and Popular Principle and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice all Wiſe Men abhor;</hi> whatever may be ſaid againſt Perſons and Adminiſtrators, who abuſe their Power and Truſt, yet that maketh not againſt the Office and Ordinance, whether Civil or Sacred if good, and in it ſelf Lawful; but if the Abuſes be as it were inſeperable, and the Office it ſelf were Apocryphal (both which as to Prelacy hold) the Plea is Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: I have Read of a <hi>Contingens raro plerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vel ad utrumlibet,</hi> but a <hi>Contingens ſemper,</hi> ſeemeth to be a Repugnancy, for what is <hi>ſemper,</hi> muſt be <hi>neceſſarium &amp; per ſe,</hi> and not contingent and by accident: and that there the fault is in the Bone may eaſily be made appear, for a Miniſter of the Goſpel cannot have a Stomach to digeſt a Lordly Prelacy with its Concomitants, till his temperature be ſo vitiate, that it incline and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34532:9"/> to all the fore-ſaid Diſtempers. 4. Theſe things did appear while the differences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued between the King and his Subjects. O but to ſee Presbyterian Government in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe under his Majeſty's Eye and Protection, how good and pleaſant were it? How Beautiful then would Ordinances be? How orderly Church Meetings? How would Love and Concord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, when thus the occaſion of Jealouſies and Animoſities were cut off? Such as know any thing in Hiſtory, or what is now done in thoſe places where the Prelates domineer, know how the Mitre always doeth encroach on the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and Civil Powers, which begetteth ſuch diſtraction, that often it breaketh forth into Tumults and Civil Wars: But where is there ſuch Order, Beauty and Concord, as in the Presbyterian Churches? How exactly do they walk? How tender are they of the Magiſtrates Authority, not in the leaſt encroaching on his Power and Priviledges? Who can give but one Inſtance of any ſuch Miſcarriage in Presbyteries or Synods in <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches? And wo's me, that we only among the Nations, who diſown the great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late ſhould be made to graon under the Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Yoke; for though in ſome other Churches there be Super-Intendents, yet they have no Civil Power, Title, or Place; nay, they have no Eccleſiaſtical Preheminence over their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, no power to cenſure them, no Negative Voice in Judicatories, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, and are nothing but meer Preſidents in Synods; and during the intervalls of theſe, they in nothing differ from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34532:9"/> other Miniſters: So that the Government there may be called Presbyterian, and in <hi>Swedland,</hi> where they did ſit in Parliament (but otherwiſe differed not from other Superintendents) Now as I am Informed, they are caſt off the State, and are not permitted to Sit or Vote in any Civil Court: Where ever the Prelate hath any Power or Civil Function, that place will ſoon be made ſenſible of his unfitneſs, and that he was not Created for ſuch a work.</p>
            <p>What is alledged concerning the ſuitableneſs of Prelacy to Monarchy, rather than any other form of Civil Government, is a ſuitable plea for ſuch a cauſe: For 1. Who can imagine what that Service can be which the Prelate can do to a Kingdom, and not to a Common-wealth, or what the Prince could require of him, which the States could not? 2. How clearly is this confuted by the Experiences of all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, living under Monarchical or Princely Government? And to ſpeak nothing of the State of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> after the Reformation from Popery, the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was for many years ſetled before his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip got Footing here, which was not till the fifth Century, when Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> ſent hither <hi>Palladius</hi> to create that New Order, and with what diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty that Church was brought to ſubmit to the Prelate, Hiſtorians ſhow; ſo that firſt and laſt his Lordſhip hath met with a cold welcome there; and hpapy that Church bad been, if it had never Couched under that Burthen. 3. The pretended Similitude and ſuitableneſs, which is alledged for the Foundation of that Inſtitution is Ridiculous, ſince our Prelats
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34532:10"/> Confeſs their Government to be Ariſtocratical, and not Monarchical, Condemning in their Diſputes with <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope his Aſpiring to Monarchy, and the Papal Government as Anti-chriſtian, becauſe Monarchical; ſo that if ſuitableneſs with the State muſt be the Foundation of Church Government, Prelacy according to their own Hypotheſis, muſt ſuit better with Ariſtocracy then Monarchy, and better with <hi>Holland</hi> then <hi>Britain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, you may ask what Courſe ſhall be taken, for Diſcovering what is the Right Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, and for its Eſtabliſhment?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The ſaying is not more Common then True; <hi>Artifici in ſua arte Credendum,</hi> a Man is to be Truſted in his own Art; if Rulers were deliberating how an Army ſhould be Ordered, how a Fleet Provided, a Houſe Builded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> would they not conſult expert Souldiers, Marriners, Maſons? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſhould not the Pious, Judicious, and moſt Unbyaſſed Paſtors of the Church be Conſulted concerning its Government? And where was it ever ſettled, and how can it be ſuppoſed, that it can be done aright without their Advice? Accordingly the Engliſh Parliament <hi>Anno</hi> 1643. when ſo many Grievances (tho' not ſo many as now may be) againſt the Prelates were Preſented to them, Wiſely called an Aſſembly of the moſt Judicious Divines (aſſiſted with ſome ſent from <hi>Scotland</hi>) that ever met in that Church; and thus a Beautiful Aſſembly Conſiſting of Perſons of divers Perſwaſions, of Presbyterians, Prelatical Doctors, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That all might be heard, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34532:10"/> the Truth, the more clearly Diſcovered, and the right Government Eſtabliſhed upon the moſt ſolid Foundation; yet ſo, that as to the Number, a Difference was made between the Grieved, and thoſe who had done the Injury and given the Offence; but, O if ſuch a free and full Debate were now allowed, and ſuch a Meeting Called by King and Parliament; this Propoſal is ſo Rational, that King <hi>Charles</hi> II. being Convinced how acceptable it would be, to the then Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhortly after his Reſtauration, <hi>Anno</hi> 1660. Reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Firſt Miſſive to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from <hi>Breda,</hi> wherein he promiſed, to Call with their Advice an Aſſembly of Divines for Settling of the Affairs of the Church, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, <hi>That the then Eſtabliſhment of Prelacy ſhould be no prejudice to that promiſe, he being then as reſolute to perform it as when he made it:</hi> But, that after that they had gotten ſome Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Epiſcopacy, as lately they had of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, he would Call an Aſſembly of Divines, who might without prejudice, and by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Judge what Government was beſt and moſt convenient for the Church; and now the Lord having ſet on the Throne that Illuſtrious Prince, who did ſo Sympathize with Sufferers, and was ſo Touched with our Grievances, as to undertake an Expedition accompanied with ſo much hazard by Sea and Land, and which required ſuch great Preparations, and vaſt Expence, as may be matter of Aſtoniſhment to us, and of Praiſe to God, who ſtirred him up for ſuch a Noble Work, and followed his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34532:11"/> Pious and Magnanimous Enterprize with ſuch admirable Succeſs; When (I pray) and by whom, could we expect ſuch a Redreſs of Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, ſuch a Reformation of Religion and Manners, and ſuch Order both in Church and State, as while his Majeſty now Sways the Scepter? And by whom could we look for the Performance of the Solemn promiſe made by King <hi>Charles</hi> II. if not now by his Royal Nephew Set on the Throne?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 1. The Meeting-Houſes are but few in Compariſon of the Churches, to which the Multitude, as well as the Great Ones, Reſort, and thus there may be more dificulty in getting the right Government of the Church Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, then ſome apprehend. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> It is well known, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtand ſo much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Formalities of Law and Order, (what ever thoſe Laws be, or the pretended Order) that great and ſmall pay ſuch a deference to thoſe as is ſcarce Credible in ſuch a Judicious and Excellent People, but once take away thoſe Conſtitutions, and let but an equal Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty by Law be Allowed to Diſſenters and Conformiſts, and then it will appear, who do Cordially own and will ſtand for Prelacy, and who not. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> If once Presbyterian Government were Eſtabliſhed by Law, and Prelacy ſent a Packing, as <hi>Anno</hi> 1643. and if there were ſuch a Nomination of Worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for Overſeeing the ſetting up of Synods, Presbyteries, Claſſical and Congregational, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Conſtitution and way of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Members to a National Synod, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34532:11"/> was <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See,</hi> the Form of Church Government to be uſed in the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> agreed upon by the Lords and Commons Aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, after Advice had with the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines, <hi>Die Mart.</hi> 29. <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1648.</note> Appointed by both Houſes of Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. Then it would appear what Eſteem the Conforming Clergy as ſuch (altho' otherwiſe there be not a few amongſt thoſe, who for their Learning, Piety and Zeal againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, deſerve to be had in Reverence) would have in <hi>England,</hi> and that the Church would not be troubled with their Meeting-Houſes, nor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny concern themſelves in providing a Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for them; Nay nay, for when there was ſuch Liberty for Petitions, Remonſtrances, Complaints, there was not ſo much as one Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (according to what I can learn) offered in their behalf, nor any Complaint made for Aboliſhing the Prelacy, Service-Book and Rabble of Popiſh Ceremonies; And then <hi>Secondly,</hi> It would be conſidered what a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage all this while the Presbyterians have been at, becauſe the Legal Stipends and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion were ſettled on, and ſecured to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, and that they were put to provide Meeting-Houſes and Maintenance for Non-Conforming Miniſters.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Some may yet Object, That the Senſe of the Nation can hardly be known, but by their Repreſentatives in Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Thus not the Senſe of the Nation, but of thoſe who had Vote in the Elections,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34532:12"/> and that ſo many of thoſe who were Elected do own the Hierarchy, may be matter of Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> No not of thoſe, if it be conſidered, that in the late Election of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to the Parliament, reſpect was had to the Proteſtant Religion, to which ſuch ſad things were deſigned by former Governours, and ſince many of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as it is Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat from its worſt part, not its Orthodox Faith, but it <hi>Romiſh</hi> Government) having Zealouſly appeared againſt Popery, not a few of thoſe were Choſen meerly upon that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, without any regard had to their Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concerning Church Government. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to many of the Electors, there might have been ſomething of Policy in that Choiſe (which altho' I do not Commend, yet I cannot Conceal) while they did conſider how that the Prelats and Clergy had Strengthened the Hands of our Kings in Eſtabliſhing an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and Illegal Power by their Votes in Parliament, and Preaching to the People the Unaccountableneſs of Kings for their Actings, and that it was the Duty of Subjects to Obey their Commands, not once Mentioning any Limitation; and crying out againſt Defenſive Arms, as an Invention of the Devil, for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving all who durſt own the ſame in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Guilt of Treaſon and Damnation; and thus hath put the late King in a Capacity to do all the miſchief we Groaned under and feared, thought fit to chuſe ſuch to deſtroy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh all thoſe Pillars of Tyranny and Popery, which their Party had Erected, and thus
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34532:12"/> might ſee what Teachers they had hearkened to, and might be Convinced (I will not ſay ſelf-Condemned) if they any more owned ſuch Teachers and Guides; and hence there may be yet ſome ground of hope, that thoſe Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Gentlemen who have not yet appeared againſt the Hierarchy, will in due time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what Conſcience, Religion, and their Honour, calls for at their Hands. But what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hath been, or may be their Carriage, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parliament may offer a better, and more true Account of the Senſe of the Nation; <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator ictus ſapit;</hi> Men will know whom they may and ſhould Truſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 3. Tuſh (may the Prelats ſay) we need not (altho' we do) fear, having ſo many Acts of Parliaments, Engagements, Promiſes (altho' none from the Scripture) for our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> But we hope the Acts of <hi>Britiſh</hi> Parliaments are not like the Laws of <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which could not be alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, altho' to the better, and for the Emolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Church and State; we know who ſaid <hi>we have a Law, and by that Law Christ muſt die:</hi> But, <hi>Secondly,</hi> What if many of thoſe Laws and Promiſes were Founded upon a very Caſual ſuppoſition, and were no Engagements to Continue Prelacy in the Church; but to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Benefices and Liberties with Prelates, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til their Office be found to be a Grievance, and a great Obſtruction of the Welfare and Happineſs of Church and Kingdom. 3. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> But what do they Prattle, what a Reproach
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34532:13"/> is it to the King and Parliament to allege (and yet not ſtrange to find Prelats do ſo) that it is not in their Power to Redreſs Greivances, or to hearken to the ſad Complaints of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed? Reaſon, Juſtice, Conſcience, will ſay, let Equity get a hearing before an Impartial Judge not Byaſſed by Conſtitutions, Acts, Deeds, Cuſtom, Practices, which can never (ſay Lawyers) preſcribe againſt Piety, Juſtice, Truth, or the Publick Good. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> All Promiſes and Engagements Founded on a Legal Eſtabliſhment, if the Law be juſtly alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Cancelled, fall to the Ground with thoſe Laws, and no more oblige; and whatever the Legal Proviſion be, no Promiſe nor En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement ought to be <hi>Vinculum iniquit atis,</hi> nor can by any moved with the fear of God be alledged for obliging to do Evil, or to obſtruct the good and happineſs of Church and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Obj.</hi> But ſhould there be no regard had of theſe Prelates, who being ſenſible of the Evil of their way, in complying with the late Kings in all their Methods, for Eſtabliſhing their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government, and for Introducing of Popery, at length, Zealouſly appeared againſt Popery?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. The Zeal of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Prelates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery appeared in their Addreſs to the late King, wherein they Proclaimed Him <hi>the Darling of Heaven, and wiſhed the Necks of his Enemies</hi> (of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and all his Army) to be given to him; and that he might
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34532:13"/> find that ſucceſs he had met with againſt <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> and <hi>Argyle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 2. As to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelates, as I abhor all Methods of Cruelty, Severity, Malice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, as being a reproach to the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſo I am far from deſiring that any good Work ſhould want a ſuitable Reward.</p>
            <p>But 3. It may ſeem ſtrange to hear any Sober Man boaſt of their Zeal againſt Popery; Ah who ſince the Reformation from Popery, have been the Patrons of Papiſts in <hi>Britain,</hi> but Prelates, by ſetting ſo many Weak, Ignorant, Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Scandalous Parſons and Curats, over Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations? And thus diſpoſing the People, 1. to Atheiſm, 2. to Popery, and whatever Religion the Court would repreſent to them, 3. By being a Tool in the Kings Hand, for bearing down of thoſe who ſtood in the Gap, and were Zealous againſt all Popiſh Innovations, 4. by Inſtilling in the People the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance and Abſolute Obedience; yea, they came that length, that one of them (<hi>viz.</hi> Prelate <hi>H.</hi>) in a Sermon, told his Hearers, <hi>That the Diſtinction between Active and Paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was founded upon Diſloyalty, and ſounded an Alarm to Rebellion; that if the Pope could lay as good a claim to Infallability, as our King, the World would hear of it.</hi> And do not theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen well deſerve to be accounted the Pillars of the Proteſtant Religion?</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As to thoſe few, who did late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear, it would be conſidered upon what occaſion they turned Sail. 1. Did any of them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34532:14"/> once mutter till their Hands were bound, that they could no more Perſecute the Innocent? 2. Then their Indignation at the Liberty grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Diſſenters, rather than their Zeal againſt Popery, ſet them to work; to which 3. add their Selfiſh Zeal for their Carnal Intereſt, when they perceived their Court to decline; and that Popiſh Prieſts had the Kings Ear, &amp; lay neareſt his Heart, and began to enter and poſſes their charges; they ſuppoſed it to be high time to break off their Silence, and Eſpouſe the honeſt Plea of the Reformed Religion, for ſecuring their Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Dignities; and now to teſtify their Zeal for for the True Religion, they muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe for an Exemption from the Oath of Allegiance, to a King, Zealous for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, whom His Majeſty muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in all their pretended Rights, though they will not acknowledge his Juſt Right and deſerved Dignity.</p>
            <p>But for Concluſion, Thoſe are times of great hopes and Expectation, and our Grievances have made ſuch a noiſe in <hi>Europe,</hi> that all are waiting for ſuch a Redreſs and Reformation as may Anſwer the Deſires and Prayers of the Grieved and Oppreſſed. But if this be all the Fruit, that our Springs are again ſent to Run in their former Muddy Channel; and if as one lately complained, <hi>Thoſe who would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us, be ſuffered to be our Inſtructors; and our Common Enemies to Teach us our Politicks, what will the World ſay of us?</hi> And Ah! how may <hi>Rome</hi> Inſult over us and Rejoyce? <hi>If Hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34532:14"/> maketh the Heart Sick,</hi> Hope fruſtrated (eſpecially in ſuch a promiſing Seaſon) muſt break the Heart. But, O what an Honour and Name of Renown will it be to ſuch as God will make Inſtrumental in Reforming his Church, and what Rich reward may they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from their Maſter, when all their Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Excellency will be laid in the Duſt? Now let us wait, looking up to him who can put it in the Hearts of King and Rulers to do this thing, which would be ſo wel-pleaſing to God, and ſo acceptable to his People.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
